<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<article doi="10.15252/msb.20188290"><fig id="24699"><title>.</title><label>Figure 1</label><graphic href="https://api.sourcedata.io/file.php?figure_id=24699"/><sd-panel panel_id="67773">First, we generated databases of all the putative <sd-pretag id="sdPretag1815751355sm" type="cell" role="component">ORFs</sd-pretag> encoded by the genomes of 109 different bacteria. The database of <em><sd-pretag id="sdPretag2076785918sd" parent-tag-id="4">M. pneumoniae</sd-pretag></em> was used to perform the shotgun MS and <sd-pretag id="sdPretag1805150695sd" parent-tag-id="2">RNA-Seq</sd-pretag> studies that were aimed at evaluating the coverage and performance of experimental approaches in the discovery of SEPs. In a parallel, experiment-independent manner, RanSEPs performed <em>in silico</em> predictions of potential novel proteins in the database. Results coming from both experimental and computational approaches are integrated in a validation step using a set of 570 SEPs characterized both in this work and in previous studies. Finally, RanSEPs predictions for the 109 bacterial genomes are combined together to assess the functional diversity and importance of predicted SEPs. The second part of the figure highlights how RanSEPs functions. In step 0 (grey box), RanSEPs detects annotated standard proteins (purple) and <sd-pretag id="sdPretag2006641385sm" type="geneprod" role="assayed">SEPs</sd-pretag> (yellow). By BlastP, non-conserved standard and SEP proteins are detected (pink and light pink, respectively). In parallel, protein features are computed and filtered by Recursive Feature Elimination. These features are combined with general features of biological interest. In step 1 (yellow box), RanSEPs randomly subsets annotated standard and small proteins into a positive (green and yellow), a feature (blue and yellow) and a negative (pink and light pink) set from the bulk of non-conserved sequences. During step 2 (blue box), specific features that vary with each iteration are appended. In step 3 (purple box), the labelled positive and negative sets are divided into training and test sets. Step 4 (green box) consists of collecting the classifiers and classification task results, and computing the final statistics and scores for all the sequences. Step 0 is only run once and then it is out of the iteration process. Steps 1 to 3 are repeated as many times as iterations selected by the user. Step 4 is computed at the end to integrate the results of each iteration. <graphic href="https://api.sourcedata.io/file.php?panel_id=67773"/></sd-panel></fig><fig id="24700"><title>.</title><label>Figure 2</label><graphic href="https://api.sourcedata.io/file.php?figure_id=24700"/><sd-panel panel_id="67774">Evaluation of <sd-tag id="sdTag1" source="sdapi" category="assay" entity_type="None" role="None" text="expression" ext_ids="OBI_0000615" ext_dbs="" in_caption="True" ext_names="protein expression profiling" ext_tax_ids="" ext_tax_names="" ext_urls="http://www.ontobee.org/ontology/OBI?iri=http://purl.obolibrary.org/obo/">expression</sd-tag> by <sd-tag id="sdTag2" source="sdapi" category="assay" entity_type="None" role="None" text="RNA-Seq" ext_ids="BAO_0003027" ext_dbs="" in_caption="True" ext_names="rna-seq method" ext_tax_ids="" ext_tax_names="" ext_urls="https://bioportal.bioontology.org/ontologies/BAO/?p=classes&amp;conceptid=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.bioassayontology.org%2Fbao%23">RNA-Seq</sd-tag> and number of peptides required to detect an annotated protein by <sd-tag id="sdTag3" source="sdapi" category="assay" entity_type="None" role="None" text="MS" ext_ids="BAO_0000055" ext_dbs="" in_caption="True" ext_names="mass spectrometry" ext_tax_ids="" ext_tax_names="" ext_urls="https://bioportal.bioontology.org/ontologies/BAO/?p=classes&amp;conceptid=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.bioassayontology.org%2Fbao%23">MS</sd-tag> in <em><sd-tag id="sdTag4" source="sdapi" category="None" entity_type="organism" role="component" text="M. pneumoniae" ext_ids="272634" ext_dbs="" in_caption="True" ext_names="Mycoplasma pneumoniae M129" ext_tax_ids="" ext_tax_names="" ext_urls="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/taxonomy/">M. pneumoniae</sd-tag></em>. The plot represents the relationship between <sd-tag id="sdTag5" source="sdapi" category="assay" entity_type="None" role="None" text="expression" ext_ids="OBI_0000615" ext_dbs="" in_caption="True" ext_names="protein expression profiling" ext_tax_ids="" ext_tax_names="" ext_urls="http://www.ontobee.org/ontology/OBI?iri=http://purl.obolibrary.org/obo/">expression</sd-tag> levels (average <sd-tag id="sdTag6" source="sdapi" category="assay" entity_type="None" role="None" text="expression" ext_ids="OBI_0000615" ext_dbs="" in_caption="True" ext_names="protein expression profiling" ext_tax_ids="" ext_tax_names="" ext_urls="http://www.ontobee.org/ontology/OBI?iri=http://purl.obolibrary.org/obo/">expression</sd-tag> from <sd-tag id="sdTag7" source="sdapi" category="assay" entity_type="None" role="None" text="RNA-Seq" ext_ids="BAO_0003027" ext_dbs="" in_caption="True" ext_names="rna-seq method" ext_tax_ids="" ext_tax_names="" ext_urls="https://bioportal.bioontology.org/ontologies/BAO/?p=classes&amp;conceptid=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.bioassayontology.org%2Fbao%23">RNA-Seq</sd-tag> data) and number of possible unique tryptic peptides (UTPs) for two sets of studied proteins: detected (blue dots) and not detected (orange dots) by <sd-tag id="sdTag8" source="sdapi" category="assay" entity_type="None" role="None" text="MS" ext_ids="BAO_0000055" ext_dbs="" in_caption="True" ext_names="mass spectrometry" ext_tax_ids="" ext_tax_names="" ext_urls="https://bioportal.bioontology.org/ontologies/BAO/?p=classes&amp;conceptid=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.bioassayontology.org%2Fbao%23">MS</sd-tag>. B) Evaluation of thresholds and artefactual signals in <sd-tag id="sdTag9" source="sdapi" category="assay" entity_type="None" role="None" text="MS" ext_ids="BAO_0000055" ext_dbs="" in_caption="True" ext_names="mass spectrometry" ext_tax_ids="" ext_tax_names="" ext_urls="https://bioportal.bioontology.org/ontologies/BAO/?p=classes&amp;conceptid=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.bioassayontology.org%2Fbao%23">MS</sd-tag> data. The histogram represents the total number of SEP proteins detected in 116 shotgun MS experiments with 1 UTP, 1 UTP and 1NUTP, or ≥2 UTPs for three categories. Color code: annotated (blue bars), putative new (orange bars), and decoy set (gray bars). C) Number of SEPs detected by increasing the number of experiments. Color code is the same as in panels B. Each line represents the accumulated number of different SEPs detected (Y-axis) when combining 1 to 116 <sd-tag id="sdTag10" source="sdapi" category="assay" entity_type="None" role="None" text="MS" ext_ids="BAO_0000055" ext_dbs="" in_caption="True" ext_names="mass spectrometry" ext_tax_ids="" ext_tax_names="" ext_urls="https://bioportal.bioontology.org/ontologies/BAO/?p=classes&amp;conceptid=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.bioassayontology.org%2Fbao%23">MS</sd-tag> datasets (X-axis) from <em><sd-tag id="sdTag11" source="sdapi" category="None" entity_type="organism" role="component" text="M. pneumoniae" ext_ids="272634" ext_dbs="" in_caption="True" ext_names="Mycoplasma pneumoniae M129" ext_tax_ids="" ext_tax_names="" ext_urls="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/taxonomy/">M. pneumoniae</sd-tag>.</em> Each line has an associated error that is shaded and represents the standard deviation within combinations of datasets (e.g., x=80 will present the average number of proteins detected taking every combination of datasets in groups of 80 samples). <graphic href="https://api.sourcedata.io/file.php?panel_id=67774"/></sd-panel></fig><fig id="24701"><title>.</title><label>Figure 3</label><graphic href="https://api.sourcedata.io/file.php?figure_id=24701"/><sd-panel panel_id="67785">Feature weight prediction in <em><sd-pretag id="sdPretag541218942sd" parent-tag-id="4">M. pneumoniae</sd-pretag></em>. Weights of the different features considered in the classification by RanSEPs. Bars indicate the global averaged variance that each feature explains by itself along with its associated standard deviation (black line). <graphic href="https://api.sourcedata.io/file.php?panel_id=67785"/></sd-panel><sd-panel panel_id="67786">Method accuracy comparative. Receiver operating characteristic curve for <sd-pretag id="sdPretag1752380428sm" type="geneprod" role="component">RanSEPs</sd-pretag> (orange) and five additional tools (blue gradient). The closer a curve to the left-hand border, the more accurate the tool. The area under the curve (AUC) associated with each method is presented, with values closer to 1 indicating a more accurate method. The dashed grey line represents a classifier that assigns the coding class randomly. <graphic href="https://api.sourcedata.io/file.php?panel_id=67786"/></sd-panel><sd-panel panel_id="67787">Boxplot representing the relationship between <sd-pretag id="sdPretag130315624sm" type="geneprod" role="assayed">RanSEPs</sd-pretag> positive ('RanSEPs+', score≥0.5) and negative ('<sd-pretag id="sdPretag1146828924sm" type="geneprod" role="assayed">RanSEPs</sd-pretag>-', score&lt;0.5) SEPs predictions and associated <sd-pretag id="sdPretag465636002sm" type="subcellular" role="component">RCV</sd-pretag> (<sd-pretag id="sdPretag498451128sm" type="subcellular" role="component">ribosome</sd-pretag> profiling ratio coverage, in log<sub>2</sub>) in <em>E. <sd-pretag id="sdPretag965928705sm" type="organism" role="component">coli</sd-pretag></em>. Only annotations ≤300 nucleotides in length were included. As positive and negative controls, we considered annotated SEPs ('Annotated') and non-coding RNAs ('ncRNAs'), respectively. Annotations within RanSEPs+, RanSEPs- and ncRNAs overlapping with known annotated genes were excluded. Annotations with <sd-pretag id="sdPretag1434764230sm" type="organism" role="component">RCV=0</sd-pretag>.0 are filtered out and the number within the box represents the percentage of values in that class that are kept in the comparative. Along the top, p-values computed by Mann-Whitney rank test are indicated. <graphic href="https://api.sourcedata.io/file.php?panel_id=67787"/></sd-panel></fig><fig id="24702"><title>.</title><label>Figure 4</label><graphic href="https://api.sourcedata.io/file.php?figure_id=24702"/><sd-panel panel_id="67781">Clustered heat map using Nearest Point algorithm and representing the weights of different features in 109 bacterial <sd-pretag id="sdPretag179088111sm" type="subcellular" role="component">genomes</sd-pretag>, and the clustering relations between features (top dendrogram) and species (side dendrogram). Rightmost light-orange and light-blue bars are included to differentiate the two main clusters. Numbers in the right <sd-pretag id="sdPretag7177273sm" type="tissue" role="component">vertical</sd-pretag> axis are short references representing the names of the bacterial genomes (Dataset EV15). The right three columns represent biological features not used in the classification. The ratio of the percentage of <sd-pretag id="sdPretag1576220470sm" type="geneprod" role="intervention">SEPs</sd-pretag> compared to the median value are colored as blue and orange for ≤13.16% of SEPs and &gt;13.16%, respectively. Blue and orange colors in the %GC column represent genomes with ≤38% and &gt;38% GC content (median value=38), respectively. Genome size column separates species into small-genome bacteria (≤1.5Mb, blue) and large-genome bacteria (&gt;1.5Mb, orange). <graphic href="https://api.sourcedata.io/file.php?panel_id=67781"/></sd-panel></fig><fig id="24703"><title>.</title><label>Figure 5</label><graphic href="https://api.sourcedata.io/file.php?figure_id=24703"/><sd-panel panel_id="67791">Landscape of the SEPs with functional annotations in NCBI considering 109 bacterial <sd-pretag id="sdPretag1877283950sm" type="subcellular" role="component">genomes</sd-pretag> (Number of SEPs = 25,229 SEPs). <graphic href="https://api.sourcedata.io/file.php?panel_id=67791"/></sd-panel><sd-panel panel_id="67792">Functional inference of the predicted SEPs (N=11,238) as determined using BlastP against <sd-pretag id="sdPretag731998909sm" type="geneprod" role="assayed">NCBI</sd-pretag>-annotated SEPs having an associated function (N=5,175). The color code associated with each category is the same as in panel A. <graphic href="https://api.sourcedata.io/file.php?panel_id=67792"/></sd-panel></fig></article>