<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<article doi="10.15252/embr.202050069"><fig id="32978"><title>.</title><label>Figure 1</label><graphic href="https://api.sourcedata.io/file.php?figure_id=32978"/><sd-panel panel_id="105241">Ribbon diagrams of the (M/E)<sub>2</sub> dimer extracted from the structure on virions (<sd-pretag id="sdPretag200793424sm" type="geneprod" role="assayed">PDB</sd-pretag>:5O6A) [10], in side (left panel) and bottom (right panel) views with M in brown and E colored according to domains: domain I, red; domain II, yellow; domain III, blue; stem, green; transmembrane (TM) segments, grey; fusion loop (FL), orange. The <graphic href="https://api.sourcedata.io/file.php?panel_id=105241"/></sd-panel></fig><fig id="32979"><title>.</title><label>Figure 2</label><graphic href="https://api.sourcedata.io/file.php?figure_id=32979"/><sd-panel panel_id="107111">A. The structure of the <sd-pretag id="sdPretag1206928470sm" type="tissue" role="component">sE</sd-pretag>-linker* <sd-pretag id="sdPretag1489368385sm" type="tissue" role="component">trimer</sd-pretag> is displayed as ribbons colored by domains as in Figure 1. The previously determined structure of the TBEV sE401v trimer (PDB 1URZ, [15]) is superposed in light grey with fusion loops (FL) in orange, highlighting the disordered domain II tip in the new structure. The two subdomains of domain II, base and tip, are indicated. Disulfide bonds are shown as dark grey sticks. The residues of the stem are displayed as sticks color-coded according to atom type, with carbon atoms green. <p>B. Close-up view of the sE-linker* trimer with one subunit colored as in (A) and the others in grey. The segment connecting helix <em>α</em>A to the <em>η</em>3 3/10 helical turn (see Appendix Fig S1) of the adjacent subunit is shown as sticks colored according to atom-type with carbon atoms light grey. Broken lines mark polar interactions of the stem with surrounding residues (with distances ranging between 2.7Å and 3.4Å). An open arrow marks the C-terminal end of the sE401v trimer structure reported previously (PDB 1URZ).</p> <p>C. For comparison, the same region of the stem is represented for the <sd-pretag id="sdPretag483098840sm" type="geneprod" role="assayed">DENV-1</sd-pretag> sE structure (PDB 4GSX, [19]), using the same color scheme.</p> <graphic href="https://api.sourcedata.io/file.php?panel_id=107111"/></sd-panel></fig><fig id="32981"><title>.</title><label>Figure 3</label><graphic href="https://api.sourcedata.io/file.php?figure_id=32981"/><sd-panel panel_id="103865">Left panel, (M/E)<sub>2</sub> dimer (PDB 5O6A, [10]) colored as in Figure 1. For clarity, <sd-pretag id="sdPretag1870270265sm" type="tissue" role="component">residues</sd-pretag> downstream E <sd-pretag id="sdPretag1697929928sm" type="geneprod" role="component">Gln404</sd-pretag> were deleted, and only residues 1 to 20 of M are shown in tube representation. The framed region is enlarged in the middle panel, with the pre-fusion E/M heterodimer (E: grey; M: brown) and the post-fusion E trimer (color-coded as domains) superimposed on helices <em>α</em>A and <em>α</em>B, illustrating the common site occupied by M and by the E stem at different stages of the <sd-pretag id="sdPretag1941527052sm" type="organism" role="component">flavivirus</sd-pretag> <sd-pretag id="sdPretag1650319055sm" type="subcellular" role="component">cycle</sd-pretag>. E and M run in opposite directions within the <sd-pretag id="sdPretag958505792sm" type="geneprod" role="assayed"><em>α</em>A</sd-pretag>/B groove, interacting with the same domain II residues. Right panel: close-ups of the interactions with residues displayed as sticks. Top, residue <sd-pretag id="sdPretag993331748sm" type="geneprod" role="component">Ile4</sd-pretag> of M takes the place of Phe403 of the stem. The bottom panel illustrates the alternative interactions made by the <sd-pretag id="sdPretag178499417sm" type="tissue" role="component">strictly</sd-pretag> conserved <sd-pretag id="sdPretag178132115sm" type="geneprod" role="assayed">Trp219</sd-pretag> side chain with the main chain of M in pre-fusion and of the stem in post-fusion forms. In both, top and bottom panels, stem and M residues are labeled in green and brown, respectively. <graphic href="https://api.sourcedata.io/file.php?panel_id=103865"/></sd-panel><sd-panel panel_id="103866">pH-dependent dissociation of E and M. <sd-tag id="sdTag14" source="sdapi" category="None" entity_type="organism" role="component" text="TBEV" ext_ids="11084" ext_dbs="" in_caption="True" ext_names="Tick-borne encephalitis virus" ext_tax_ids="" ext_tax_names="" ext_urls="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/taxonomy/">TBEV</sd-tag> preparations treated at <sd-tag id="sdTag17" source="sdapi" category="physical" entity_type="None" role="None" text="pH 8" ext_ids="" ext_dbs="" in_caption="True" ext_names="" ext_tax_ids="" ext_tax_names="" ext_urls="">pH 8</sd-tag> (left) and <sd-tag id="sdTag18" source="sdapi" category="physical" entity_type="None" role="None" text="pH 6" ext_ids="" ext_dbs="" in_caption="True" ext_names="" ext_tax_ids="" ext_tax_names="" ext_urls="">pH 6</sd-tag> (right) were solubilized with <sd-tag id="sdTag6" source="sdapi" category="None" entity_type="molecule" role="component" text="Triton X-100" ext_ids="CHEBI:9750" ext_dbs="" in_caption="True" ext_names="Triton X-100" ext_tax_ids="" ext_tax_names="" ext_urls="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/chebi/searchId.do?chebiId=">Triton X-100</sd-tag> and subjected to <sd-tag id="sdTag7" source="sdapi" category="assay" entity_type="None" role="None" text="sucrose gradient centrifugation" ext_ids="OBI_0600051" ext_dbs="" in_caption="True" ext_names="gradient separation" ext_tax_ids="" ext_tax_names="" ext_urls="http://www.ontobee.org/ontology/OBI?iri=http://purl.obolibrary.org/obo/">sucrose gradient centrifugation</sd-tag>. The fractions were analyzed by <sd-tag id="sdTag8" source="sdapi" category="assay" entity_type="None" role="None" text="SDS-PAGE" ext_ids="OBI_0600053" ext_dbs="" in_caption="True" ext_names="electrophoresis" ext_tax_ids="" ext_tax_names="" ext_urls="http://www.ontobee.org/ontology/OBI?iri=http://purl.obolibrary.org/obo/">SDS-PAGE</sd-tag> and <sd-tag id="sdTag9" source="sdapi" category="assay" entity_type="None" role="None" text="densitometry" ext_ids="BAO_0000464" ext_dbs="" in_caption="True" ext_names="densitometric scan" ext_tax_ids="" ext_tax_names="" ext_urls="https://bioportal.bioontology.org/ontologies/BAO/?p=classes&amp;conceptid=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.bioassayontology.org%2Fbao%23">densitometry</sd-tag>. Representative examples of at least two independent experiments are shown. Positions of E dimers (D) and E trimers (T) in the gradients are indicated. <graphic href="https://api.sourcedata.io/file.php?panel_id=103866"/></sd-panel></fig><fig id="32983"><title>.</title><label>Figure 4</label><graphic href="https://api.sourcedata.io/file.php?figure_id=32983"/><sd-panel panel_id="103867">All diagrams are aligned at the left and at the same scale, using the full-length E protein (Ev, top line) and sE401v (second line), derived from virions, as reference. Recombinant constructs are shown below the dashed line: sE400r, sE401r, sE404r (containing 6 N-terminal <sd-pretag id="sdPretag1006901722sm" type="molecule" role="intervention">amino acids</sd-pretag> of H1), sE412r (containing H1), sE419r (containing H1 and H2), sE428r (containing H1, H2 and CS) and sE448r (containing the whole stem). Abbreviations EK and StT indicate heterologous sequences corresponding to an <sd-pretag id="sdPretag1964150935sm" type="geneprod" role="assayed">enterokinase</sd-pretag>-specific cleavage site and a strep-tag used for affinity purification, respectively, added at the C-terminal end of each construct. <graphic href="https://api.sourcedata.io/file.php?panel_id=103867"/></sd-panel><sd-panel panel_id="103868"><sd-tag id="sdTag39" source="sdapi" category="assay" entity_type="None" role="None" text="Trimer stability" ext_ids="BAO_0002804" ext_dbs="" in_caption="True" ext_names="protein stability assay" ext_tax_ids="" ext_tax_names="" ext_urls="https://bioportal.bioontology.org/ontologies/BAO/?p=classes&amp;conceptid=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.bioassayontology.org%2Fbao%23">Trimer stability</sd-tag> expressed as percentage of the fraction detected in the trimer peak and normalized with respect to the corresponding Ev fraction in <sd-tag id="sdTag26" source="sdapi" category="assay" entity_type="None" role="None" text="sedimentation analyses" ext_ids="" ext_dbs="" in_caption="True" ext_names="" ext_tax_ids="" ext_tax_names="" ext_urls="">sedimentation analyses</sd-tag> after incubation at 70°C relative to 37°C (100%). Data are from at least three independent experiments. <graphic href="https://api.sourcedata.io/file.php?panel_id=103868"/></sd-panel></fig><fig id="32985"><title>.</title><label>Figure 5</label><graphic href="https://api.sourcedata.io/file.php?figure_id=32985"/><sd-panel panel_id="105250">Difference in <sd-tag id="sdTag20" source="sdapi" category="None" entity_type="molecule" role="assayed" text="deuterium" ext_ids="CHEBI:29237" ext_dbs="" in_caption="True" ext_names="deuterium atom" ext_tax_ids="" ext_tax_names="" ext_urls="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/chebi/searchId.do?chebiId=">deuterium</sd-tag> <sd-tag id="sdTag21" source="sdapi" category="assay" entity_type="None" role="None" text="uptake" ext_ids="" ext_dbs="" in_caption="True" ext_names="" ext_tax_ids="" ext_tax_names="" ext_urls="">uptake</sd-tag> by sE404r and sE419r trimers (<em>D</em><sub>404</sub>-<em>D</em><sub>419</sub><em>). Left panel, <sd-tag id="sdTag24" source="sdapi" category="assay" entity_type="None" role="None" text="deuteration" ext_ids="" ext_dbs="" in_caption="True" ext_names="" ext_tax_ids="" ext_tax_names="" ext_urls="">deuteration</sd-tag> difference for each peptide reported against the 1-p value obtained via</em> Student's <em>t</em>-test <em>between the two different constructs. In the right panel, peptides are reported as short horizontal lines, with length and position corresponding to the peptide length and location along the protein sequence (x-axis) and with their <sd-tag id="sdTag47" source="sdapi" category="assay" entity_type="None" role="None" text="deuteration delta" ext_ids="" ext_dbs="" in_caption="True" ext_names="" ext_tax_ids="" ext_tax_names="" ext_urls="">deuteration delta</sd-tag> on the y-axis. In both panels, red (positive) and blue (negative) indicate changes above the</em> Student's <em>t</em>-test <em>threshold, and in grey those not reaching this threshold. Four peptides, termed</em> <sd-tag id="sdTag43" source="sdapi" category="assay" entity_type="None" role="None" text="HDX" ext_ids="OBI_0001976" ext_dbs="" in_caption="True" ext_names="hydrogen/deuterium exchange assay" ext_tax_ids="" ext_tax_names="" ext_urls="http://www.ontobee.org/ontology/OBI?iri=http://purl.obolibrary.org/obo/">HDX</sd-tag>-<em>a,</em> <sd-tag id="sdTag45" source="sdapi" category="assay" entity_type="None" role="None" text="HDX" ext_ids="OBI_0001976" ext_dbs="" in_caption="True" ext_names="hydrogen/deuterium exchange assay" ext_tax_ids="" ext_tax_names="" ext_urls="http://www.ontobee.org/ontology/OBI?iri=http://purl.obolibrary.org/obo/">HDX</sd-tag>-<em>b,</em> <sd-tag id="sdTag44" source="sdapi" category="assay" entity_type="None" role="None" text="HDX" ext_ids="OBI_0001976" ext_dbs="" in_caption="True" ext_names="hydrogen/deuterium exchange assay" ext_tax_ids="" ext_tax_names="" ext_urls="http://www.ontobee.org/ontology/OBI?iri=http://purl.obolibrary.org/obo/">HDX</sd-tag>-<em>c and</em> <sd-tag id="sdTag46" source="sdapi" category="assay" entity_type="None" role="None" text="HDX" ext_ids="OBI_0001976" ext_dbs="" in_caption="True" ext_names="hydrogen/deuterium exchange assay" ext_tax_ids="" ext_tax_names="" ext_urls="http://www.ontobee.org/ontology/OBI?iri=http://purl.obolibrary.org/obo/">HDX</sd-tag>-<em>d, were identified as showing a strong increase in <sd-tag id="sdTag31" source="sdapi" category="assay" entity_type="None" role="None" text="deuteration" ext_ids="" ext_dbs="" in_caption="True" ext_names="" ext_tax_ids="" ext_tax_names="" ext_urls="">deuteration</sd-tag> in sE404r compared to sE419r. The same pattern was observed in the comparison between sE404r and sE428r, whereas no difference deemed "significant" by the same test was seen when comparing sE419r with sE428r (see Fig EV3).</em> <graphic href="https://api.sourcedata.io/file.php?panel_id=105250"/></sd-panel><sd-panel panel_id="105251">Middle panel: <sd-pretag id="sdPretag1357812848sd" type="subcellular" role="component">ribbons</sd-pretag> representation of the sE trimer (PDB 1URZ) colored according to domains with high <sd-pretag id="sdPretag1203473861sd" parent-tag-id="43">HDX</sd-pretag> regions <em>a</em> and <em>c</em> boxed and highlighted in light grey. The central box marks the domain I-II hinge. Residues 401 and 403, which occupy the <graphic href="https://api.sourcedata.io/file.php?panel_id=105251"/></sd-panel></fig><fig id="32986"><title>.</title><label>Figure 6</label><graphic href="https://api.sourcedata.io/file.php?figure_id=32986"/><sd-panel panel_id="103858">Binding sites of <sd-pretag id="sdPretag1646704264sd" type="cell" role="component">mabs</sd-pretag> (highlighted with ovals) were mapped by mutational analysis (A1 and A2) or by neutralization escape (A3 and B4). The residues affecting binding are represented as <sd-pretag id="sdPretag357437794sd" type="geneprod" role="component">white</sd-pretag> patches on the surface of the sE trimer (PDB 1URZ) color-coded as domains. The <em>a-d</em> surface segments identified by the <sd-pretag id="sdPretag1458650037sd" parent-tag-id="43">HDX</sd-pretag>-MS experiments are shown as grey patches. <graphic href="https://api.sourcedata.io/file.php?panel_id=103858"/></sd-panel><sd-panel panel_id="103859">Blocking <sd-tag id="sdTag1" source="sdapi" category="assay" entity_type="None" role="None" text="ELISA" ext_ids="BAO_0000134" ext_dbs="" in_caption="True" ext_names="ELISA" ext_tax_ids="" ext_tax_names="" ext_urls="https://bioportal.bioontology.org/ontologies/BAO/?p=classes&amp;conceptid=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.bioassayontology.org%2Fbao%23">ELISA</sd-tag> with mabs A1, A2, A3 and B4. Serial dilutions of the trimers were pre-incubated with a predetermined concentration of the respective mabs. The fraction of mab not blocked by the antigen was detected in <sd-tag id="sdTag2" source="sdapi" category="assay" entity_type="None" role="None" text="ELISA" ext_ids="BAO_0000134" ext_dbs="" in_caption="True" ext_names="ELISA" ext_tax_ids="" ext_tax_names="" ext_urls="https://bioportal.bioontology.org/ontologies/BAO/?p=classes&amp;conceptid=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.bioassayontology.org%2Fbao%23">ELISA</sd-tag> with <sd-tag id="sdTag3" source="sdapi" category="None" entity_type="organism" role="component" text="TBEV" ext_ids="11084" ext_dbs="" in_caption="True" ext_names="Tick-borne encephalitis virus" ext_tax_ids="" ext_tax_names="" ext_urls="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/taxonomy/">TBEV</sd-tag>-coated plates (Materials and Methods). The bar charts show the results expressed relative to the reactivity with the sE401v trimer. Data are from at least three independent experiments. <graphic href="https://api.sourcedata.io/file.php?panel_id=103859"/></sd-panel></fig><fig id="32987"><title>.</title><label>Figure 7</label><graphic href="https://api.sourcedata.io/file.php?figure_id=32987"/><sd-panel panel_id="103857">One protomer extracted from the post-fusion trimer of <sd-pretag id="sdPretag1668057222sm" type="geneprod" role="intervention">TBEV</sd-pretag> sE (PDB 1URZ [15] + stem residues 402-404 modeled from the sE-linker* structure) displayed next to a protomer extracted from the complete trimer of hairpins of the <sd-pretag id="sdPretag1371036331sm" type="geneprod" role="assayed">RVFV</sd-pretag> Gc (PDB <sd-pretag id="sdPretag1173799046sm" type="geneprod" role="assayed">6EGU</sd-pretag> [36]) class II fusion protein. Both proteins are color-coded by domains as in Figure 1 but with the two segments that make up domain II distinguished in yellow and brown. An arrow at the top marks a disulfide bond conserved across all class II viral fusion proteins (shown in black). In RVFV Gc, the stem reaches the FL and its C-terminal end is stabilized by interactions with a GPL head group (shown as ball-and-stick) bound in a cavity underneath the FL, with its <sd-pretag id="sdPretag1477436992sm" type="molecule" role="component">glycerol</sd-pretag> moiety interacting with the conserved disulfide bond. The most C-terminal residue visualized in the <sd-pretag id="sdPretag1664720570sd" parent-tag-id="3">TBEV</sd-pretag> sE-linker* structure, Gln404, is about 15 <sd-pretag id="sdPretag1853237376sm" type="molecule" role="intervention">amino acids</sd-pretag> short of reaching the FL, which would correspond roughly to position 419 at the beginning of the <sd-pretag id="sdPretag2000772155sm" type="subcellular" role="component">CS</sd-pretag>. The location of CS within the stem is indicated in the panel below. <graphic href="https://api.sourcedata.io/file.php?panel_id=103857"/></sd-panel></fig><fig id="32988"><title>.</title><label>Figure 8</label><graphic href="https://api.sourcedata.io/file.php?figure_id=32988"/><sd-panel panel_id="106548">Postulated organization of the amphipathic H3 helix in the post-fusion trimer. Left panel: proposed arrangement of the H3 helix in our post-fusion trimer <sd-pretag id="sdPretag1898616475sd" category="assay">model</sd-pretag>, lying flat on the fused <sd-pretag id="sdPretag1295339338sd" type="subcellular" role="component">membrane</sd-pretag> (in light orange) and projecting the TM segments (not drawn) away from the trimer axis. Second panel: potential conformation of the sE448r trimer, with the H3 helices trimerizing via their hydrophobic surfaces. Third panel: the sE-linker construct. As the linker is not long enough (only 8 residues), the H3 helix cannot trimerize as in the full-stem sE448r trimer. It would be exposed on the sides of the trimer, potentially leading to <sd-pretag id="sdPretag1105820882sd" type="subcellular" role="component">aggregation</sd-pretag>. Right-<sd-pretag id="sdPretag874088326sd" type="tissue" role="component">hand</sd-pretag> panel: the sE-linker* <sd-pretag id="sdPretag1349701155sd" type="molecule" role="reporter">did</sd-pretag> not lead to <sd-pretag id="sdPretag96896626sd" type="subcellular" role="component">aggregation</sd-pretag>, and at high concentrations it crystallized in a form that had the tip disordered. Trimerization of the three H3 helices in the trimer may have caused this effect, as they must displace the trimer tips in order to oligomerize. This is a further measure of the highly dynamic breathing <sd-pretag id="sdPretag972615840sd" category="assay">behavior</sd-pretag> of the E trimers, as the <sd-pretag id="sdPretag390165232sd" category="assay">sequence</sd-pretag> required to complete the stem <sd-pretag id="sdPretag647313066sd" type="geneprod" role="component">zipper</sd-pretag> was absent from this construct. <graphic href="https://api.sourcedata.io/file.php?panel_id=106548"/></sd-panel><sd-panel panel_id="106549">Schematic of the viral surface in the mature particle, with E and M in side view, color coded as in Fig 1. The breathing <sd-pretag id="sdPretag1111845355sd" category="assay">behavior</sd-pretag> within and between E dimers, transiently exposing the fusion loop and regions normally buried at the dimer-dimer interface, is indicated by curved lines. A vertical arrow points to the hinge between domains I and II, a region that supports <sd-pretag id="sdPretag312375231sd" parent-tag-id="15">E protein</sd-pretag> breathing. ii). Dissociation of E dimers in the acidic milieu of an <sd-pretag id="sdPretag1746308583sd" type="subcellular" role="component">endosome</sd-pretag>, exposing the FLs and allowing their insertion into the <sd-pretag id="sdPretag1732887658sd" type="subcellular" role="component">endosomal</sd-pretag> <sd-pretag id="sdPretag137807204sd" type="subcellular" role="component">membrane</sd-pretag>. iii). Upon fusion loop insertion, the E <sd-pretag id="sdPretag1375772565sd" type="molecule" role="component">proteins</sd-pretag> form "extended intermediate" trimers bridging the two <sd-pretag id="sdPretag1169684084sd" type="subcellular" role="component">membranes</sd-pretag>. Curved blue arrows indicate the subsequent re-location of domain III, in blue, to the sides of the trimer to initiate the "hairpin" conformation of the <sd-pretag id="sdPretag1895669250sd" type="organism" role="component">individual</sd-pretag> subunits of the post-fusion trimer. iv). Upon relocation of domain III, the upstream part of the stem becomes anchored to the the <graphic href="https://api.sourcedata.io/file.php?panel_id=106549"/></sd-panel></fig></article>