<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<article doi="10.15252/msb.20209701"><fig id="44886"><title>.</title><label>Figure 1</label><graphic href="https://api.sourcedata.io/file.php?figure_id=44886"/><sd-panel panel_id="128950">The two steps of GENDULF: <strong>(Step 1)</strong> Mine transcriptomics of healthy disease-relevant tissues to identify PMs, which are genes that are differentially under-expressed when the GCD is lowly expressed. GENDULF does not compute a correlation across the whole range of expression values, but specifically searches only for a significant association at the lower level range, as shown in the region boxed in the left scatter plot, where the dots are in blue and the y-axis is labeled 'PM' for `potential modifier'. The scatter plot on the upper right depicts an example of relationship between expression of the GCD and another gene in which GENDULF is not expected to find the other gene as a modifier, and hence the y-axis is labeled non-PM expression. <strong>(Step 2)</strong> Evaluate the expression of PMs identified in step 1 in transcriptomic data sets containing both diseased and control samples to find a subset of PMs that we label as DPMs (left graphs)- PM genes that are not down regulated in the disease tissues. <graphic href="https://api.sourcedata.io/file.php?panel_id=128950"/></sd-panel></fig><fig id="44887"><title>.</title><label>Figure 2</label><graphic href="https://api.sourcedata.io/file.php?figure_id=44887"/><sd-panel panel_id="128951">(A)-(C) Upper panels: Scatter plots associating the expression of the GCD (<sd-pretag id="sdPretag1388713317sd" type="geneprod" role="component">CFTR</sd-pretag>) vs. identified PMs (A) EHF, (B) <em>SLC6A14</em>, and (C) <em>SFTPA2</em> in healthy <sd-pretag id="sdPretag1739093291sd" type="tissue" role="component">lung</sd-pretag> tissues from GTEx. Bottom Panels: Boxplots associating the expression of the identified DPMs in case-control studies; the expression of (A) EHF, (B) <em>SLC6A14</em>, and (C) <em>SFTPA2</em> in severe and mild CF and in healthy controls. For all boxplots, center lines indicate medians, box edges represent the interquartile range, whiskers extend to the most extreme data points not considered outliers, and the outliers are plotted individually. Points are defined as outliers if they are greater than <em>q</em><sub>3</sub> + <em>w</em> × (<em>q</em><sub>3</sub>-<em>q</em><sub>1</sub>) or <em><q><sub>1</sub>-<em>w</em> × (<em>q</em><sub>3</sub> − <em>q</em><sub>1</sub>), where <em>w</em> is the maximum whisker length, and <em>q</em><sub>1</sub> and <em>q</em><sub>3</sub> are the 25th and 75th percentiles of the sample data, respectively. There are five severe (red), four mild (orange) and eleven control (blue) biological replicates. Data information: ** is P-value&lt;0.01 and *** is P-value&lt;0.001, using the permutation test The P-values in panels A, B, C are for the hyper-geometric enrichment test.</q></em> <graphic href="https://api.sourcedata.io/file.php?panel_id=128951"/></sd-panel><sd-panel panel_id="128952">(D) Map of coincidence of the low expression (lowest 10% of expression levels) of the 7 top DPMs with the low expression of <sd-pretag id="sdPretag1125365762sd" type="geneprod" role="component">CFTR</sd-pretag> in GTEx <sd-pretag id="sdPretag535291961sd" type="tissue" role="component">lung</sd-pretag> samples (lowest 10% of expression levels, when symptoms would be present in CF patients (Ramalho <em>et al</em>, 2002; Kerem <em>et al</em>, 1997); each small rectangle inside the big rectangle represents one individual; all presented samples are those with low <sd-pretag id="sdPretag2017363749sd" type="geneprod" role="component">CFTR</sd-pretag> expression. Dark blue rectangles indicate samples with low expression of the listed DPM). <graphic href="https://api.sourcedata.io/file.php?panel_id=128952"/></sd-panel><sd-panel panel_id="128953">(E), (F) Upper panels: scatter plot associating the expression of the GCD (<sd-pretag id="sdPretag1162505936sd" type="geneprod" role="component">CFTR</sd-pretag>) vs. identified PMs in healthy <sd-pretag id="sdPretag1091721156sd" type="tissue" role="component">colon</sd-pretag> GTEx tissue; the expression of <sd-pretag id="sdPretag168774232sd" type="geneprod" role="component">CFTR</sd-pretag> (X-axis) vs. that of (E) <em>CLCA1</em> and (F) <em>SLC4A4</em>, respectively, in healthy <sd-pretag id="sdPretag1712957861sd" type="tissue" role="component">colon</sd-pretag> tissues. Bottom panels: Boxplots associating the expression of the identified DPMs in case-control studies; the expression of (E) <em>CLCA1</em> and (F) <em>SLC4A4</em> in <sd-pretag id="sdPretag628951868sd" type="tissue" role="component">colon</sd-pretag> tissues from CF and healthy controls. Empirical P-value significance is indicated qualitatively for two thresholds. There are sixteen CF (red) and thirteen control (blue) biological replicates. Data information: ** is P-value&lt;0.01 and *** is P-value&lt;0.001, using the permutation test The P-values in panels , E, F are for the hyper-geometric enrichment test. <graphic href="https://api.sourcedata.io/file.php?panel_id=128953"/></sd-panel><sd-panel panel_id="128954">(G) The p-values assigned by GENDULF to genes within chr11p12-p13, chr6p21.3, chr3q29 and chrXq22-q23 chromosomal segments, ordered by their location. The lower dashed line represents a significance threshold corrected for the number of genes evaluated and the upper dashed line represents a significance threshold corrected for all genes and transcripts in GTEx, with alpha = 0.05. Data information: ** is P-value&lt;0.01 and *** is P-value&lt;0.001, using the permutation test The P-values in panels G are for the hyper-geometric enrichment test. <graphic href="https://api.sourcedata.io/file.php?panel_id=128954"/></sd-panel></fig><fig id="44888"><title>.</title><label>Figure 3</label><graphic href="https://api.sourcedata.io/file.php?figure_id=44888"/><sd-panel panel_id="128955">(A)-(C) Previously reported modifiers. Upper panels: Scatter plots associating the expression of the GCD (SMN1) vs. identified PMs in healthy GTEx muscle tissues (left panels) and <sd-pretag id="sdPretag760955244sd" type="tissue" role="component">spinal cord</sd-pretag> tissues (right panels); the expression of <em>SMN1</em> (X-axis) vs. that of (A) <em>HNRNPU</em>, (B) <em>SF1</em> and (C) <em>SRSF4</em>. Bottom Panels: Boxplots associating the expression of the identified DPMs in case-control studies; the expression of (A) <em>HNRNPU</em>, (B) SF1, and (C) <em>SRSF4</em> in <sd-pretag id="sdPretag1217872311sd" type="geneprod" role="component">SMA</sd-pretag> and in healthy control muscle (left panels) and <sd-pretag id="sdPretag1749963395sd" type="tissue" role="component">spinal cord</sd-pretag> (right panels) tissues. Data information: Empirical P-values significance is indicated for two thresholds (** is P-value&lt;0.01 and *** is P-value&lt;0.001, using the permutation test are for the hyper-geometric enrichment test. There are six control (blue) and eleven <sd-pretag id="sdPretag1465861671sd" type="geneprod" role="component">SMA</sd-pretag> biological replicates (red) from muscle tissues and four control (blue) and six <sd-pretag id="sdPretag1451296353sd" type="geneprod" role="component">SMA</sd-pretag> biological replicates (red) from <sd-pretag id="sdPretag2115274920sd" type="tissue" role="component">spinal cord</sd-pretag> tissues. The Reads Per Kilobase Million (RPKM) measure was used in the GTEx dataset, and the Fragments Per Kilobase Million (FPKM) measure was used in the <sd-pretag id="sdPretag1860846116sd" type="geneprod" role="component">SMA</sd-pretag> case-control dataset. <graphic href="https://api.sourcedata.io/file.php?panel_id=128955"/></sd-panel><sd-panel panel_id="128956">(D)-(E) Candidate modifiers. Upper panels: Scatter plots associating the expression of the GCD (SMN1) vs. identified PMs in healthy GTEx muscle tissues (left panels) and <sd-pretag id="sdPretag157540513sd" type="tissue" role="component">spinal cord</sd-pretag> tissues (right panels); the expression of SMN1 (X-axis) vs. that of the negative DPM modifiers (D) <sd-pretag id="sdPretag1857390849sd" parent-gene-tag-id="1" parent-protein-tag-id="13"><em>U2AF1</em></sd-pretag> and (E) <em>HNRNPA0</em>. Bottom Panels: Boxplots associating the expression of the identified DPMs in case-control studies; the expression of (D) <sd-pretag id="sdPretag389702598sd" parent-gene-tag-id="1" parent-protein-tag-id="13"><em>U2AF1</em></sd-pretag> and (E) <em>HNRNPA0</em> in <sd-pretag id="sdPretag281107026sd" type="geneprod" role="component">SMA</sd-pretag> and in healthy control muscle (left panels) and <sd-pretag id="sdPretag1237064826sd" type="tissue" role="component">spinal cord</sd-pretag> (middle panels) tissues. Right panels show the levels of these predicted modifiers in healthy muscle samples with low ratio of <sd-pretag id="sdPretag815653882sd" parent-tag-id="2">SMN2</sd-pretag>-FL to <sd-pretag id="sdPretag345465650sd" parent-tag-id="2">SMN2</sd-pretag>∆7 and those with high ratio of <sd-pretag id="sdPretag1704472491sd" parent-tag-id="2">SMN2</sd-pretag>-FL to <sd-pretag id="sdPretag718825113sd" parent-tag-id="2">SMN2</sd-pretag>∆7. Data information: Empirical P-values significance is indicated for two thresholds (** is P-value&lt;0.01 and *** is P-value&lt;0.001, using the permutation test The P-values denoted in the upper panels of and E are for the hyper-geometric enrichment test. There are six control (blue) and eleven <sd-pretag id="sdPretag1539316842sd" type="geneprod" role="component">SMA</sd-pretag> biological replicates (red) from muscle tissues and four control (blue) and six <sd-pretag id="sdPretag849653782sd" type="geneprod" role="component">SMA</sd-pretag> biological replicates (red) from <sd-pretag id="sdPretag995840267sd" type="tissue" role="component">spinal cord</sd-pretag> tissues. The Reads Per Kilobase Million (RPKM) measure was used in the GTEx dataset, and the Fragments Per Kilobase Million (FPKM) measure was used in the <sd-pretag id="sdPretag540801273sd" type="geneprod" role="component">SMA</sd-pretag> case-control dataset. <graphic href="https://api.sourcedata.io/file.php?panel_id=128956"/></sd-panel></fig><fig id="44889"><title>.</title><label>Figure 4</label><graphic href="https://api.sourcedata.io/file.php?figure_id=44889"/><sd-panel panel_id="128957">(A)-(D) Expression of (A) <em>HNRNPA0</em>, (B) <sd-pretag id="sdPretag216463686sd" parent-gene-tag-id="1" parent-protein-tag-id="13"><em>U2AF1</em></sd-pretag>, (C) <em>SF3B3,</em> or (D) <em>NECAP1</em> 72 hours post-transfection with either <sd-pretag id="sdPretag26818442sd" parent-tag-id="2">SMN2</sd-pretag> SSO or knockdown of each target using siRNAs in HEK293T cells. (E)-(G) Expression of (E) <sd-pretag id="sdPretag1578451018sd" parent-tag-id="2">SMN2</sd-pretag>-FL<em>,</em> (F) <sd-pretag id="sdPretag1358950324sd" parent-tag-id="2">SMN2</sd-pretag>∆7<em>,</em> or (G) SMN1-FL following <sd-pretag id="sdPretag1376112457sd" parent-tag-id="2"><em>SMN2</em></sd-pretag> SSO or siRNA transfection (n=4). Data information: *<em>p</em> &lt; 0.05; **<em>p</em> &lt; 0.01; ***<em>p</em> &lt; 0.001; ****<em>p</em> &lt; 0.0001; empirical p-values are determined by a simulation and sampling method The error bars show the Standard Error of Mean (SEM). Data from A-G represent 4 biological replicates. Three technical replicates were performed during <sd-pretag id="sdPretag47964208sd" category="assay">qPCR</sd-pretag> for each biological replicate and averaged. Scrambled siRNA condition for each experiment was set to 1. <graphic href="https://api.sourcedata.io/file.php?panel_id=128957"/></sd-panel><sd-panel panel_id="128958">(H)-(J) mRNA expression of (H) <em><sd-tag id="sdTag1" source="sdapi" category="None" entity_type="gene" role="assayed" text="U2AF1" ext_ids="7307" ext_dbs="" in_caption="True" ext_names="U2AF1" ext_tax_ids="9606" ext_tax_names="Homo sapiens" ext_urls="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/gene/">U2AF1</sd-tag></em>, (I) <sd-tag id="sdTag2" source="sdapi" category="None" entity_type="gene" role="assayed" text="SMN2" ext_ids="6607" ext_dbs="" in_caption="True" ext_names="SMN2" ext_tax_ids="9606" ext_tax_names="Homo sapiens" ext_urls="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/gene/">SMN2</sd-tag>-FL, or (J) <sd-tag id="sdTag3" source="sdapi" category="None" entity_type="gene" role="assayed" text="SMN2" ext_ids="6607" ext_dbs="" in_caption="True" ext_names="SMN2" ext_tax_ids="9606" ext_tax_names="Homo sapiens" ext_urls="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/gene/">SMN2</sd-tag>∆7 in <sd-tag id="sdTag4" source="sdapi" category="disease" entity_type="None" role="None" text="SMA" ext_ids="DOID:12377" ext_dbs="" in_caption="True" ext_names="spinal muscular atrophy" ext_tax_ids="" ext_tax_names="" ext_urls=" https://identifiers.org/">SMA</sd-tag> <sd-tag id="sdTag5" source="sdapi" category="None" entity_type="organism" role="component" text="patient" ext_ids="9606" ext_dbs="" in_caption="True" ext_names="Homo sapiens" ext_tax_ids="" ext_tax_names="" ext_urls="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/taxonomy/">patient</sd-tag>-derived <sd-tag id="sdTag6" source="sdapi" category="None" entity_type="cell" role="component" text="fibroblasts" ext_ids="CL:0000057" ext_dbs="" in_caption="True" ext_names="fibroblast" ext_tax_ids="" ext_tax_names="" ext_urls=" https://identifiers.org/">fibroblasts</sd-tag> (red bars) 72 hours post-transfection with <sd-tag id="sdTag7" source="sdapi" category="None" entity_type="gene" role="intervention" text="SMN2" ext_ids="6607" ext_dbs="" in_caption="True" ext_names="SMN2" ext_tax_ids="9606" ext_tax_names="Homo sapiens" ext_urls="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/gene/">SMN2</sd-tag> SSO, scrambled siRNA, or <em/><sd-tag id="sdTag8" source="sdapi" category="None" entity_type="gene" role="intervention" text="U2AF1" ext_ids="7307" ext_dbs="" in_caption="True" ext_names="U2AF1" ext_tax_ids="9606" ext_tax_names="Homo sapiens" ext_urls="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/gene/"><em>U2AF1</em></sd-tag> siRNA at the indicated dose. Unaffected, <sd-tag id="sdTag9" source="sdapi" category="disease" entity_type="None" role="None" text="SMA" ext_ids="DOID:12377" ext_dbs="" in_caption="True" ext_names="spinal muscular atrophy" ext_tax_ids="" ext_tax_names="" ext_urls=" https://identifiers.org/">SMA</sd-tag> carrier <sd-tag id="sdTag10" source="sdapi" category="None" entity_type="cell" role="component" text="fibroblasts" ext_ids="CL:0000057" ext_dbs="" in_caption="True" ext_names="fibroblast" ext_tax_ids="" ext_tax_names="" ext_urls=" https://identifiers.org/">fibroblasts</sd-tag> (blue bars) treated with scrambled siRNA. Data information: *<em>p</em> &lt; 0.05; **<em>p</em> &lt; 0.01; ***<em>p</em> &lt; 0.001; ****<em>p</em> &lt; 0.0001; empirical p-values are determined by a simulation and sampling method The error bars show the Standard Error of Mean (SEM). Data represent 3 biological replicates. Three technical replicates were performed during <sd-tag id="sdTag11" source="sdapi" category="assay" entity_type="None" role="None" text="qPCR" ext_ids="BAO_0002090" ext_dbs="" in_caption="True" ext_names="quantitative reverse transcription PCR" ext_tax_ids="" ext_tax_names="" ext_urls="https://bioportal.bioontology.org/ontologies/BAO/?p=classes&amp;conceptid=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.bioassayontology.org%2Fbao%23">qPCR</sd-tag> for each biological replicate and averaged. Scrambled siRNA condition for each experiment was set to 1. <graphic href="https://api.sourcedata.io/file.php?panel_id=128958"/></sd-panel><sd-panel panel_id="128959">(K) Representative <sd-tag id="sdTag12" source="sdapi" category="assay" entity_type="None" role="None" text="Western blot" ext_ids="BAO_0002424" ext_dbs="" in_caption="True" ext_names="western blot" ext_tax_ids="" ext_tax_names="" ext_urls="https://bioportal.bioontology.org/ontologies/BAO/?p=classes&amp;conceptid=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.bioassayontology.org%2Fbao%23">Western blot</sd-tag>. (L)-(M) Quantification of <sd-tag id="sdTag21" source="sdapi" category="assay" entity_type="None" role="None" text="protein expression" ext_ids="OBI_0000615" ext_dbs="" in_caption="True" ext_names="protein expression profiling" ext_tax_ids="" ext_tax_names="" ext_urls="http://www.ontobee.org/ontology/OBI?iri=http://purl.obolibrary.org/obo/">protein expression</sd-tag> of (L) <em/><sd-tag id="sdTag13" source="sdapi" category="None" entity_type="protein" role="assayed" text="U2AF1" ext_ids="Q01081" ext_dbs="" in_caption="True" ext_names="U2AF1" ext_tax_ids="9606" ext_tax_names="Homo sapiens" ext_urls="https://www.uniprot.org/uniprot/"><em>U2AF1</em></sd-tag> or (M) <sd-tag id="sdTag14" source="sdapi" category="None" entity_type="protein" role="assayed" text="SMN" ext_ids="Q16637" ext_dbs="" in_caption="True" ext_names="SMN1" ext_tax_ids="9606" ext_tax_names="Homo sapiens" ext_urls="https://www.uniprot.org/uniprot/">SMN</sd-tag> normalized to <sd-tag id="sdTag15" source="sdapi" category="None" entity_type="protein" role="normalizing" text="GAPDH" ext_ids="P04406" ext_dbs="" in_caption="True" ext_names="GAPDH" ext_tax_ids="9606" ext_tax_names="Homo sapiens" ext_urls="https://www.uniprot.org/uniprot/">GAPDH</sd-tag> (n=3). Data information: *<em>p</em> &lt; 0.05; **<em>p</em> &lt; 0.01; ***<em>p</em> &lt; 0.001; ****<em>p</em> &lt; 0.0001; empirical p-values are determined by a simulation and sampling method The error bars show the Standard Error of Mean (SEM). Data represent 3 biological replicates. <graphic href="https://api.sourcedata.io/file.php?panel_id=128959"/></sd-panel></fig></article>