<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<article doi="10.15252/msb.20199174"><fig id="30580"><title>: Inferring direct regulation using many TF induction experiments.</title><label>Figure 1</label><graphic href="https://api.sourcedata.io/file.php?figure_id=30580"/><sd-panel panel_id="102469">A. In each experiment, one transcriptional regulator with an inducible promoter is rapidly overexpressed in response to 1 µM β-estradiol. <graphic href="https://api.sourcedata.io/file.php?panel_id=102469"/></sd-panel><sd-panel panel_id="102470">B. Example of three genes (labeled <em>B</em>, <em>C</em>, and <em>D</em>) responding with different kinetics following induction of regulator <em>A</em>. <graphic href="https://api.sourcedata.io/file.php?panel_id=102470"/></sd-panel><sd-panel panel_id="102471">C. Hypothetical example of a regulatory cascade in which an induced transcriptional regulator <em>A</em> directly inhibits <em>C</em> and directly activates <em>B</em>. <em>B</em>, in turn, directly activates <em>D</em>. <graphic href="https://api.sourcedata.io/file.php?panel_id=102471"/></sd-panel><sd-panel panel_id="102472">D. In practice, we <sd-pretag id="sdPretag1704427570sd" type="molecule" role="component">don</sd-pretag>'t know that <em>A</em> regulates <em>D</em> via <em>B</em> and instead want to infer such regulatory relationships. In this example, direct regulation of <em>D</em> by <em>B</em> is only one hypothesis that is consistent with the data - <sd-pretag id="sdPretag904933538sd" type="cell" role="component">all</sd-pretag> viable hypotheses are shown by dashed lines. <em>A</em> could directly activate <em>D</em>, <em>C</em> could inhibit <em>D</em>, or <em>A</em> could regulate an unmeasured confounder <em>U</em> which is the true regulator. Direct regulation by a variable <em>Y</em>, which is independent of <em>A</em>, is not possible <sd-pretag id="sdPretag444803079sd" type="subcellular" role="component">since</sd-pretag> the <sd-pretag id="sdPretag2036644224sd" category="time">timecourse</sd-pretag> begins at steady state. <graphic href="https://api.sourcedata.io/file.php?panel_id=102472"/></sd-panel><sd-panel panel_id="102473">E. Integrating the <em>A</em> induction <sd-pretag id="sdPretag316108142sd" category="time">timecourse</sd-pretag> with a second induction <sd-pretag id="sdPretag554366808sd" category="time">timecourse</sd-pretag>, which perturbs <em>B</em> without perturbing <em>A</em> or <em>C</em>, allows us to narrow down <em>D</em>'s possible sources of regulation. In this case, <em>U</em> may still be a possibility if it is remains correlated with <em>B</em>. <graphic href="https://api.sourcedata.io/file.php?panel_id=102473"/></sd-panel><sd-panel panel_id="102474">F. Overview of data and analysis performed in this study. Over 200 induction experiments were constructed allowing for many opportunities to resolve ambiguous regulation. <graphic href="https://api.sourcedata.io/file.php?panel_id=102474"/></sd-panel></fig><fig id="30581"><title>.</title><label>Figure 2</label><graphic href="https://api.sourcedata.io/file.php?figure_id=30581"/><sd-panel panel_id="102475">A. Heatmap summary of <sd-tag id="sdTag1" source="sdapi" category="None" entity_type="protein" role="intervention" text="Aft1" ext_ids="A0A6V8RJC0" ext_dbs="" in_caption="True" ext_names="SCNYR20_0003016200" ext_tax_ids="4932" ext_tax_names="Saccharomyces cerevisiae" ext_urls="https://www.uniprot.org/uniprot/">Aft1</sd-tag> induction experiment showing all genes that change with |log2(fold-change)| &gt; 1.5. <graphic href="https://api.sourcedata.io/file.php?panel_id=102475"/></sd-panel><sd-panel panel_id="102476">B. Parametric summaries of representative sigmoidal activation and inhibition timecourses and impulse (double sigmoid) modeling of transitory inhibition. Sigmoids are summarized by half-<sd-pretag id="sdPretag362697635sd" type="geneprod" role="component">max</sd-pretag> time (t<sub>rise</sub>) and the asymptote (v<sub>inter</sub>), while impulses include a second half-<sd-pretag id="sdPretag1966846625sd" type="geneprod" role="component">max</sd-pretag> (t<sub>fall</sub>) time and final asymptote (v<sub>final</sub>). The strongest supported model for each timecourse is shown as a filled in <sd-pretag id="sdPretag1912038939sd" type="geneprod" role="normalizing">line</sd-pretag>, while the alternative model is shown with a dashed <sd-pretag id="sdPretag266797867sd" type="geneprod" role="normalizing">line</sd-pretag>. <graphic href="https://api.sourcedata.io/file.php?panel_id=102476"/></sd-panel><sd-panel panel_id="102477">C. K-mers <sd-pretag id="sdPretag934230519sd" category="assay">enriched</sd-pretag> in the promoters of regulated genes are overlaid on summary of each gene's t<sub>rise</sub> and v<sub>inter</sub>. Presence of the <sd-pretag id="sdPretag621196357sd" parent-tag-id="1">Aft1</sd-pretag> motif is associated with early activation, while early inhibition is associated with the PAC motif (Tod6/Dot6). <graphic href="https://api.sourcedata.io/file.php?panel_id=102477"/></sd-panel><sd-panel panel_id="102478">D. Response kinetics are overlaid on gene coordinates <sd-pretag id="sdPretag1134085688sd" type="molecule" role="component">based</sd-pretag> on synthetic lethality as a surrogate for functional similarity. Up-regulated genes are <sd-pretag id="sdPretag1575238519sd" category="assay">enriched</sd-pretag> for <sd-pretag id="sdPretag1267103140sd" type="subcellular" role="component">vesicle</sd-pretag> trafficking/glycosylation processes and down-regulated genes are <sd-pretag id="sdPretag2013930611sd" category="assay">enriched</sd-pretag> for <sd-pretag id="sdPretag1590219438sd" type="subcellular" role="component">mitochondrial</sd-pretag>/mitotic/<sd-pretag id="sdPretag2106282909sd" type="molecule" role="component">rRNA</sd-pretag> processes. <graphic href="https://api.sourcedata.io/file.php?panel_id=102478"/></sd-panel></fig><fig id="30582"><title>.</title><label>Figure 3</label><graphic href="https://api.sourcedata.io/file.php?figure_id=30582"/><sd-panel panel_id="102523">A. Using a representative <sd-pretag id="sdPretag597143663sd" parent-tag-id="1">Aft1</sd-pretag> responsive gene, <em>YHB1</em>, fold-change differences between timepoints (solid grey dots) are compared to the LASSO regression <sd-pretag id="sdPretag1658326604sd" category="assay">model</sd-pretag>'s fit (crosses). The <sd-pretag id="sdPretag1847363997sd" category="assay">model</sd-pretag>'s predicted marginal contribution of three predicted regulators (Fet3, Hmx1, and Arn2) to the combinatorial control of <em>YHB1</em> are shown with bars that sum to the <sd-pretag id="sdPretag2109896165sd" category="assay">model</sd-pretag>'s overall fit (crosses). <graphic href="https://api.sourcedata.io/file.php?panel_id=102523"/></sd-panel><sd-panel panel_id="102524">B. The <em>YHB1</em> fold-change differences fit by regression can be converted to full <sd-pretag id="sdPretag2109642317sd" category="time">timecourses</sd-pretag> to determine the marginal contributions of each regulator in driving a regulatory transition of interest (rises and falls). <graphic href="https://api.sourcedata.io/file.php?panel_id=102524"/></sd-panel><sd-panel panel_id="102525">C. Each differentially-expressed gene in the <sd-pretag id="sdPretag1276731954sd" parent-tag-id="1">Aft1</sd-pretag> experiment is laid out <sd-pretag id="sdPretag716852237sd" type="molecule" role="component">based</sd-pretag> on its kinetics and colored according to the regulator predicted to be the strongest driver of differential expression. <sd-pretag id="sdPretag38440542sd" category="assay">Model</sd-pretag>-derived fractional contributions of regulators to expression of <em>AQY2, NSR1</em>, <em>YHB1</em>, and <em>HEM25</em> are depicted as donut charts. <graphic href="https://api.sourcedata.io/file.php?panel_id=102525"/></sd-panel></fig><fig id="30583"><title>: Inferred regulator-target coefficient magnitudes are predictive of interactions in published datasets.</title><label>Figure 4</label><graphic href="https://api.sourcedata.io/file.php?figure_id=30583"/><sd-panel panel_id="102536">The rankings of observed induction responses (ascending by t<sub>rise</sub>) and predicted regulator relationships (descending by regression coefficient magnitude) were used to predict edges in multiple published networks (Costanzo 2016 and YeastNet v.3). <sd-pretag id="sdPretag1270912288sd" type="cell" role="component">All</sd-pretag> non-zero ODE regression coefficients were split into two classes, measured (predicted regulators with an induction experiment) and latent (predicted regulators without an induction experiment). <strong>A.</strong> ROC curves are shown treating interactions, which overlap with the query edges (non-zero regression coefficients), as positives and <sd-pretag id="sdPretag626500418sd" type="cell" role="component">all</sd-pretag> other entries as negatives. <graphic href="https://api.sourcedata.io/file.php?panel_id=102536"/></sd-panel><sd-panel panel_id="102537">B. The AUC of the ROC curves in A are shown as large dots, compared to random permutations (which preserve the <sd-pretag id="sdPretag923427839sd" category="assay">counts</sd-pretag> of each cause and effect but randomize their pairings) of the edge list which are shown as small dots and a boxplot of these null AUCs. Permutations with values systematically in excess of a value of 0.5, as seen when predicting genetic interactions with rise time, are likely due to hub effects where genes that tend to be predicted regulators of many targets also tend to have interactions. <graphic href="https://api.sourcedata.io/file.php?panel_id=102537"/></sd-panel></fig><fig id="30584"><title>.</title><label>Figure 5</label><graphic href="https://api.sourcedata.io/file.php?figure_id=30584"/><sd-panel panel_id="102538">Direct regulation between genes is defined <sd-pretag id="sdPretag531496010sd" type="molecule" role="component">based</sd-pretag> on causal attribution analysis and indirect regulation of an induced gene is defined if a gene is differentially expressed regardless of whether attribution analysis indicated a direct regulatory relationship. <strong>A.</strong> Edges between both genes with induction experiments and predicted regulators were formed <sd-pretag id="sdPretag1060657060sd" type="molecule" role="component">based</sd-pretag> on regulatory interactions predicted from <sd-pretag id="sdPretag1896129676sd" type="organism" role="component">individual</sd-pretag> experiments (as shown in Figure 3C). For this visualization, major regulators selected as per Figure 3C are rooted to the induced TF regardless of whether they were directly or indirectly regulated by this gene. Predicted regulators are linked to GO categories <sd-pretag id="sdPretag343440009sd" type="molecule" role="component">based</sd-pretag> on having a significant overlap with their predicted targets. Similarly, genes with an induction experiment are linked to GO categories <sd-pretag id="sdPretag1200620246sd" type="molecule" role="component">based</sd-pretag> on overlap of either direct or indirect targets with GO categories. Validated nodes (green) are genes where validation experiments confirmed a significant overlap between measured gene-regulator connections and <sd-pretag id="sdPretag554367611sd" category="assay">model</sd-pretag>-predicted coefficients. Invalidated nodes (red) are genes where validation experiments failed to confirm <sd-pretag id="sdPretag1074392109sd" category="assay">model</sd-pretag>-predicted coefficients. <strong>B.</strong> Local networks <sd-pretag id="sdPretag2132515362sd" type="molecule" role="component">based</sd-pretag> on upstream direct/indirect regulators and downstream direct targets of three validated regulators. <graphic href="https://api.sourcedata.io/file.php?panel_id=102538"/></sd-panel></fig><fig id="30585"><title>.</title><label>Figure 6</label><graphic href="https://api.sourcedata.io/file.php?figure_id=30585"/><sd-panel panel_id="102539">All genes passing hard-thresholding in each experiment are shown. K-means clustering was used to cluster responsive genes (K = 4 for Fmp48 and K = 2 for Stp4 and Hmx1) and GO slim gene-sets <sd-pretag id="sdPretag2011308083sd" category="assay">enriched</sd-pretag> in each cluster are shown. <graphic href="https://api.sourcedata.io/file.php?panel_id=102539"/></sd-panel></fig></article>