<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<article doi="10.15252/msb.20188190"><fig id="19788"><title>.</title><label>Figure 1</label><graphic href="https://api.sourcedata.io/file.php?figure_id=19788"/><sd-panel panel_id="64047"> <p><sd-pretag role="reporter" id="sdPretag1992393849sme" type="geneprod">IDR</sd-pretag>-<sd-pretag role="reporter" id="sdPretag1398632617sme" type="geneprod">Screen</sd-pretag> consists of a modular set of stages that can broadly be grouped into the experimental and computational phases. A library of random or designed <sd-pretag category="assay" id="sdPretag1660304459sd">sequences</sd-pretag> is inserted into a genome, expressed as a part of a <sd-pretag role="component" id="sdPretag250356077sd" type="molecule">protein</sd-pretag> that is used for selection (<sd-pretag category="assay" id="sdPretag1620146752sd">survival</sd-pretag> or other readouts such as fluorescence). The library is then screened to discover <sd-pretag category="assay" id="sdPretag382773441sd">sequences</sd-pretag> that are functional/non-functional <sd-pretag role="component" id="sdPretag331211130sd" type="molecule">based</sd-pretag> on the designed assay to infer functionality. Upon data processing, this dataset of experimentally validated functional and non-functional <sd-pretag category="assay" id="sdPretag754302678sd">sequences</sd-pretag> are analyzed to learn the <sd-pretag role="component" id="sdPretag1289629752sme" type="tissue">rules</sd-pretag> using Machine Learning (ML) approaches</p> <graphic href="https://api.sourcedata.io/file.php?panel_id=64047"/></sd-panel></fig><fig id="19789"><title>.</title><label>Figure 2</label><graphic href="https://api.sourcedata.io/file.php?figure_id=19789"/><sd-panel panel_id="64048"> <dl> <dt>A.</dt> <dd>Enrichment and depletion of different amino acids in the random library (log2 of frequencies of functional over non-functional sequences)</dd> </dl> <graphic href="https://api.sourcedata.io/file.php?panel_id=64048"/></sd-panel><sd-panel panel_id="64049"> <dl> <dt>B</dt> </dl> <dl> <dd>In the boxplots, the central line shows the median. Statistical significance was assessed using Wilcoxon test. Boxplots of the distribution of the values of:</dd> <dt>B.</dt> <dd>length</dd> <dt>C.</dt> <dd>pI</dd> <dt>D.</dt> <dd>hydrophobicity</dd> <dt>E.</dt> <dd>disorder content and</dd> <dt>F.</dt> <dd>helicity for sequences that are functional (green) and non-functional (red</dd> </dl> <graphic href="https://api.sourcedata.io/file.php?panel_id=64049"/></sd-panel><sd-panel panel_id="64050">.-G Statistical significance was assessed using Wilcoxon test <dl> <dt>G.</dt> <dd>Enrichment of 9aa TAD motif in functional vs. non-function sequences; ratio of with to without 9 aa TAD in functional to non-functional sequences ((219/520)/(13384/50001)</dd> </dl> <graphic href="https://api.sourcedata.io/file.php?panel_id=64050"/></sd-panel></fig><fig id="19790"><title>.</title><label>Figure 3</label><graphic href="https://api.sourcedata.io/file.php?figure_id=19790"/><sd-panel panel_id="64051"> <p>Schematic describing the <sd-pretag category="assay" id="sdPretag47529372sd">sequence</sd-pretag> space explored by the random library (left). Table listing the top 10 most important features. The relative feature importance is given as relative percentages in the last four columns. The size of the circles is scaled per method (lasso, ridge, xgboost, stacked). The direction column denotes the direction of <sd-pretag category="assay" id="sdPretag1829911198sd">enrichment</sd-pretag> of the given feature for functional <sd-pretag category="assay" id="sdPretag1729771301sd">sequences</sd-pretag> compared to non-functional <sd-pretag category="assay" id="sdPretag76559711sd">sequences</sd-pretag> (up, positive direction and down, negative direction)</p> <graphic href="https://api.sourcedata.io/file.php?panel_id=64051"/></sd-panel></fig><fig id="19791"><title>.</title><label>Figure 4</label><graphic href="https://api.sourcedata.io/file.php?figure_id=19791"/><sd-panel panel_id="64052"> <p>Heatmap of the tolerance to amino acid substitutions in WT transactivation domain sequences. The tolerance of a mutation is defined as the fraction of functional sequences over all the sequences when a specific substitution was performed. The columns (amino acid in a WT TAD that is substituted) are ordered according to decreasing tolerance (from left to right) and the rows (amino acid into which a residue in the WT TAD is substituted for) are ordered according to decreasing tolerance (from bottom to top). The cells are colored on a green to red gradient for high to low tolerance respectively. Empty tiles represent data points not present in the library</p> <graphic href="https://api.sourcedata.io/file.php?panel_id=64052"/></sd-panel><sd-panel panel_id="64053"> <p>Schematic describing the <sd-pretag category="assay" id="sdPretag1456553254sd">sequence</sd-pretag> space explored by the design library (left). Table listing the top 10 most important features. The relative feature importance is given as relative percentages in the last four columns. The size of the circles is scaled per method (lasso, ridge, xgboost, stacked). The direction column denotes the direction of <sd-pretag category="assay" id="sdPretag1490129547sd">enrichment</sd-pretag> of the given feature for functional <sd-pretag category="assay" id="sdPretag1121977386sd">sequences</sd-pretag> compared to non-functional <sd-pretag category="assay" id="sdPretag1282885003sd">sequences</sd-pretag> (up, positive direction and down, negative direction)</p> <graphic href="https://api.sourcedata.io/file.php?panel_id=64053"/></sd-panel></fig><fig id="19792"><title>.</title><label>Figure 5</label><graphic href="https://api.sourcedata.io/file.php?figure_id=19792"/><sd-panel panel_id="64054"> <p>Schematic describing the <sd-pretag category="assay" id="sdPretag258516644sd">sequence</sd-pretag> space explored by the combined library (left). Table listing the top 10 most important features. The relative feature importance is given as relative percentages in the last four columns. The size of the circles is scaled per method (lasso, ridge, xgboost, stacked). The direction column denotes the direction of <sd-pretag category="assay" id="sdPretag1223531483sd">enrichment</sd-pretag> of the given feature for functional <sd-pretag category="assay" id="sdPretag522711348sd">sequences</sd-pretag> compared to non-functional <sd-pretag category="assay" id="sdPretag1868393782sd">sequences</sd-pretag> (up, positive direction and down, negative direction)</p> <graphic href="https://api.sourcedata.io/file.php?panel_id=64054"/></sd-panel></fig><fig id="19793"><title>.</title><label>Figure 6</label><graphic href="https://api.sourcedata.io/file.php?figure_id=19793"/><sd-panel panel_id="64056"> <p><sd-tag id="sdTag69" source="sdapi" category="assay" entity_type="None" role="None" text="Spot assay" ext_ids="" ext_dbs="" in_caption="True" ext_names="" ext_tax_ids="" ext_tax_names="" ext_urls="">Spot assay</sd-tag> of designed TAD constructs . The <sd-tag id="sdTag70" source="sdapi" category="assay" entity_type="None" role="None" text="spot assay" ext_ids="" ext_dbs="" in_caption="True" ext_names="" ext_tax_ids="" ext_tax_names="" ext_urls="">spot assay</sd-tag> was performed at <sd-tag id="sdTag75" source="sdapi" category="physical" entity_type="None" role="None" text="30ºC" ext_ids="" ext_dbs="" in_caption="True" ext_names="" ext_tax_ids="" ext_tax_names="" ext_urls="">30ºC</sd-tag> (left) and during heat shock at <sd-tag id="sdTag76" source="sdapi" category="physical" entity_type="None" role="None" text="37ºC" ext_ids="" ext_dbs="" in_caption="True" ext_names="" ext_tax_ids="" ext_tax_names="" ext_urls="">37ºC</sd-tag> (right panel)</p> <graphic href="https://api.sourcedata.io/file.php?panel_id=64056"/></sd-panel></fig><fig id="19794"><title>.</title><label>Figure 7</label><graphic href="https://api.sourcedata.io/file.php?figure_id=19794"/><sd-panel panel_id="64055"> <p>Transcription factors (TFs) interact with <sd-pretag role="component" id="sdPretag277544699sd" type="molecule">DNA</sd-pretag> via the <sd-pretag role="assayed" id="sdPretag292522549sd" type="molecule">DNA</sd-pretag> binding domain (DBD, blue triangle) and to their interaction partners (grey) via their transactivation domains (TAD, green rectangle). The <sd-pretag category="assay" id="sdPretag292352536sd">enrichment</sd-pretag> for negatively charged residues leads to a local extended conformation of the TAD via intra-chain repulsions, providing the appropriate context for aromatic residues to be exposed and to bind to their interaction partners in hydrophobic binding pocket (circular inset). The aromatic residues could fit the pocket in a stochastic manner, binding in different configurations. This would result in the formation of a "fuzzy" complex. In this case, the negative charges could furthermore contribute to the affinity of binding given that the TAD-interaction surfaces often expose positively charged patches. The absence of positively charged residues, compositional bias and particular spacing of negatively charged and aromatic residues could hence be considered as giving rise to a collection of short mini motifs that collectively contributes to TAD functionality</p> <graphic href="https://api.sourcedata.io/file.php?panel_id=64055"/></sd-panel></fig></article>