<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<article doi="10.15252/msb.202110260"><fig id="43846"><title>.</title><label>Figure 1</label><graphic href="https://api.sourcedata.io/file.php?figure_id=43846"/><sd-panel panel_id="119827">(A) PCA plot using the rank-based inverse normal-transformed differential expression (DE) log fold-change values (virus-infected compared to control samples) across all the datasets analyzed. <graphic href="https://api.sourcedata.io/file.php?panel_id=119827"/></sd-panel><sd-panel panel_id="119828">(B) Visualization of the overlap of the top significant DE genes (FDR&lt;0.1) between each pair of datasets analyzed using Fisher's exact tests (Methods). The dot size corresponds to the effect size of the overlap as measured by odds ratio, and the color corresponds to the negative log10 adjusted one-sided P value (grey means below 0.05). <graphic href="https://api.sourcedata.io/file.php?panel_id=119828"/></sd-panel><sd-panel panel_id="119829">(C) Visualization of the overlap of the top significantly enriched pathways (FDR&lt;0.1) from the gene set enrichment analysis (<sd-pretag id="sdPretag41708421sd" category="assay">GSEA</sd-pretag>) between each pair of datasets analyzed using Fisher's exact tests (Methods). The meanings of dot size and color are the same as (B), dots with <sd-pretag id="sdPretag1965000879sd" type="geneprod" role="component">black</sd-pretag> borders correspond to infinity odds ratio. <graphic href="https://api.sourcedata.io/file.php?panel_id=119829"/></sd-panel><sd-panel panel_id="119830">(D) A summary visualization of the <sd-pretag id="sdPretag324862621sd" category="assay">GSEA</sd-pretag> result for the top consistently altered pathways during SARS-CoV-2 infection across the datasets, with more importance given to the various in vivo <sd-pretag id="sdPretag1159707895sd" type="organism" role="component">patient</sd-pretag> datasets (Methods). The dot color corresponds to the negative log10 adjusted P values from <sd-pretag id="sdPretag1960996244sd" category="assay">GSEA</sd-pretag>, with two sets of colors (red-orange and blue-purple) distinguishing up-regulation from down-regulation (positive or negative normalized enrichment scores, i.e. <sd-pretag id="sdPretag659703328sd" type="geneprod" role="component">NES</sd-pretag>); dot size corresponds to the absolute value of <sd-pretag id="sdPretag1834450889sd" type="geneprod" role="component">NES</sd-pretag> measuring the strength of enrichment. The left and right-<sd-pretag id="sdPretag1563034865sd" type="tissue" role="component">hand</sd-pretag> side blocks represent the pathways that tend to be consistently up-regulated and down-regulated in infected vs control samples, respectively; within each block, the pathways are ordered by negative sum of log P values across datasets (i.e. Fisher's method). <graphic href="https://api.sourcedata.io/file.php?panel_id=119830"/></sd-panel><sd-panel panel_id="119831">(E) Heatmap summarizing the landscape of metabolic pathway alterations (based on gene expression) during SARS-CoV-2 across datasets. The heatmap color corresponds to the <sd-pretag id="sdPretag79412315sd" category="assay">GSEA</sd-pretag> <sd-pretag id="sdPretag1289155670sd" type="geneprod" role="component">NES</sd-pretag> values (explained above) for KEGG metabolic pathways grouped into major categories. Only the metabolic pathways with FDR&lt;0.1 enrichment in at least one dataset are included in the heatmap. The dataset labels used in this figure correspond to those given in Table 1. <graphic href="https://api.sourcedata.io/file.php?panel_id=119831"/></sd-panel></fig><fig id="43847"><title>.</title><label>Figure 2</label><graphic href="https://api.sourcedata.io/file.php?figure_id=43847"/><sd-panel panel_id="119832">(A) Visualization of the overlap of the top DF reactions between each pair of datasets analyzed using Fisher's exact tests (Methods). The dot size corresponds to the effect size of the overlap as measured by odds ratio, and the color corresponds to the negative log10 adjusted one-sided P value (grey means below 0.05). <graphic href="https://api.sourcedata.io/file.php?panel_id=119832"/></sd-panel><sd-panel panel_id="119833">(B) A summary visualization of the metabolic pathway enrichment result for the top consistent DF reactions across the datasets, with more importance given to the various in vivo <sd-pretag id="sdPretag1488940789sd" type="organism" role="component">patient</sd-pretag> datasets (Methods). Y-axis represents the odds ratio of enrichment, the dot color corresponds to the adjusted P value from Fisher's exact tests, and dot size corresponds to the number of enriched reactions within each pathway. Half-dots plotted on the top border line correspond to infinity odds ratio values. The pathways on the X-axis are ordered by P value and only those with FDR&lt;0.1 are shown. <graphic href="https://api.sourcedata.io/file.php?panel_id=119833"/></sd-panel><sd-panel panel_id="119834">(C-E) Visualization of the relatively consistent DF patterns in selected enriched pathways. The DF results are based on metabolic modeling using the <sd-pretag id="sdPretag675601691sd" type="organism" role="component">human</sd-pretag> GEM Recon 3D (Brunk et al. 2018), but for clear visualization, the metabolic network graphs are based on the <sd-pretag id="sdPretag1772230025sd" type="organism" role="component">human</sd-pretag> GEM Recon 1 (Duarte et al. 2007) to reduce the number of metabolites and reactions displayed (Methods). Metabolites are represented by nodes, reactions are represented by directed (hyper) edges, with edge direction corresponding to the consensus reaction direction and edge color corresponding to the consensus DF direction across datasets (Methods). Red and blue colors correspond to increased and decreased fluxes, respectively; grey color corresponds to reactions not showing consistent DF changes across datasets, some of such reactions are not shown to increase clarity. (C) Pyrimidine synthesis. (D) Inositol phosphate metabolism. (E) <sd-pretag id="sdPretag1283146856sd" type="molecule" role="component">Fatty acid</sd-pretag> synthesis. Metabolites are labeled by their names in (C) or IDs in (D,E), with suffixes denoting their cellular compartments: [c] <sd-pretag id="sdPretag2043158630sd" type="subcellular" role="component">cytosol</sd-pretag>; [m] <sd-pretag id="sdPretag998666876sd" type="subcellular" role="component">mitochondria</sd-pretag>. The mapping between the IDs and metabolite names in (D,E) is given in Table EV5C. <graphic href="https://api.sourcedata.io/file.php?panel_id=119834"/></sd-panel></fig><fig id="43848"><title>.</title><label>Figure 3</label><graphic href="https://api.sourcedata.io/file.php?figure_id=43848"/><sd-panel panel_id="119835">(A) Visualization of the overlap of the top 10% MTA-predicted target reactions between each pair of datasets analyzed using Fisher's exact tests (Methods). The dot size corresponds to the effect size of the overlap as measured by odds ratio, and the color corresponds to the negative log10 adjusted one-sided P value (grey means below 0.05). <graphic href="https://api.sourcedata.io/file.php?panel_id=119835"/></sd-panel><sd-panel panel_id="119836">(B) A summary visualization of the enrichment of the top 10% MTA-predicted targets from each dataset for the antiviral hits (i.e. those whose KO inhibits SARS-CoV-2 infection) identified in the two published <sd-pretag id="sdPretag932675571sd" type="geneprod" role="component">CRISPR</sd-pretag>-<sd-pretag id="sdPretag1903310289sd" type="geneprod" role="component">Cas9</sd-pretag> screens (Wei et al. 2021 and Daniloski et al. 2021; Methods). Y-axis represents the odds ratio of enrichment, the dot color corresponds to the negative log10 adjusted one-sided P value from Fisher's exact tests, and dot size corresponds to the number of enriched target reactions. The datasets are ordered by P values, the first 8 datasets have FDR&lt;0.1. <graphic href="https://api.sourcedata.io/file.php?panel_id=119836"/></sd-panel><sd-panel panel_id="119837">(C) cases of significant enrichment (FDR&lt;0.1) of top 10% MTA-predicted targets from each dataset for the experimentally validated anti-SARS-CoV-2 drug sets from previous studies (compiled by Kuleshov et al. 2020). "Union" means the union of all drug sets. Axes and the meanings of dot color and size are similar to (B) but the axes are flipped and the adjusted P values are not log-transformed. <graphic href="https://api.sourcedata.io/file.php?panel_id=119837"/></sd-panel><sd-panel panel_id="119838">(D) significant cases of significant enrichment (FDR&lt;0.1) of top 10% MTA-predicted targets from each dataset for the host proteins involved in host-SARS-CoV-2 protein-protein interactions (combined from Stukalov et al. 2020 and Gordon et al. 2020). Axes and the meanings of dot color and size are similar to (C). <graphic href="https://api.sourcedata.io/file.php?panel_id=119838"/></sd-panel><sd-panel panel_id="119839">(E) A summary of the area under ROC curve (AUROC) value of the MTA prediction using each dataset, based on positive and negative sets (i.e. genes whose KO inhibits or promotes the viral infection, respectively) from the two published <sd-pretag id="sdPretag831799254sd" type="geneprod" role="component">CRISPR</sd-pretag>-<sd-pretag id="sdPretag557477832sd" type="geneprod" role="component">Cas9</sd-pretag> screen data (Wei et al. 2021 and Daniloski et al. 2021; Methods). The error bars (vertical lines through the dots) represent 95% confidence intervals obtained with bootstrapping. The horizontal dashed line corresponds to AUROC of 0.5 (i.e. performance of a random predictor). <graphic href="https://api.sourcedata.io/file.php?panel_id=119839"/></sd-panel><sd-panel panel_id="119841">(F) Example ROC curves from two of the best-performing datasets, one in vitro (Vero) and one in vivo (SC.Liao). The curves are colored by color gradients corresponding to the threshold of top MTA predictions. <graphic href="https://api.sourcedata.io/file.php?panel_id=119841"/></sd-panel><sd-panel panel_id="119840">(G) Summary of the metabolic pathways significantly enriched (FDR&lt;0.1) by the final list of consensus candidate targets identified across datasets (Methods). The axes and the meanings of dot color and size are similar to (B) except for that the axes are flipped. <graphic href="https://api.sourcedata.io/file.php?panel_id=119840"/></sd-panel></fig><fig id="43849"><title>.</title><label>Figure 4</label><graphic href="https://api.sourcedata.io/file.php?figure_id=43849"/><sd-panel panel_id="119842">(A) A schematic illustration of the siRNA assay in Caco-2 cells infected with SARS-CoV-2 to validate the antiviral efficacies of the consensus predicted metabolic targets. Caco-2 cells were transfected with siRNAs for 48 h prior to infection with SARS-CoV-2 (MOI=0.1). Four replicates were performed for each target. At 48 h post-infection, cells were subjected to staining with SARS-CoV-2 nucleoprotein (N) antibody and <sd-pretag id="sdPretag1155170680sd" parent-tag-id="9">DAPI</sd-pretag>, and then imaged to determine the percentage of infected cells after each target knockdown (Methods). <graphic href="https://api.sourcedata.io/file.php?panel_id=119842"/></sd-panel><sd-panel panel_id="119843">(B) Quantification of <sd-tag id="sdTag1" source="sdapi" category="None" entity_type="organism" role="assayed" text="SARS-CoV-2" ext_ids="2697049" ext_dbs="" in_caption="True" ext_names="Severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2" ext_tax_ids="" ext_tax_names="" ext_urls="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/taxonomy/">SARS-CoV-2</sd-tag> infection. After the siRNA knockdown of each target, <sd-tag id="sdTag51" source="sdapi" category="assay" entity_type="None" role="None" text="viral infection" ext_ids="OBI_0001187" ext_dbs="" in_caption="True" ext_names="infectious agent detection assay" ext_tax_ids="" ext_tax_names="" ext_urls="http://www.ontobee.org/ontology/OBI?iri=http://purl.obolibrary.org/obo/">viral infection</sd-tag> was quantified as mean log2 fold-change (log2FC) of the percentage of <sd-tag id="sdTag2" source="sdapi" category="None" entity_type="organism" role="assayed" text="SARS-CoV-2" ext_ids="2697049" ext_dbs="" in_caption="True" ext_names="Severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2" ext_tax_ids="" ext_tax_names="" ext_urls="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/taxonomy/">SARS-CoV-2</sd-tag>+ cells relative to the mean of scrambled non-targeting siRNAs ("SCRAMBLED", green dots; accordingly the mean log2FC value of scrambled non-targeting siRNAs was normalized to zero). Predicted positive targets ("TARGETING", grey dots), predicted negative targets ("NEG", blue dots) and positive controls ("POS", red dots, including <sd-tag id="sdTag3" source="sdapi" category="None" entity_type="gene" role="component" text="ACE2" ext_ids="59272" ext_dbs="" in_caption="True" ext_names="ACE2" ext_tax_ids="9606" ext_tax_names="Homo sapiens" ext_urls="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/gene/">ACE2</sd-tag> and <sd-tag id="sdTag4" source="sdapi" category="None" entity_type="gene" role="component" text="TMPRSS2" ext_ids="7113" ext_dbs="" in_caption="True" ext_names="TMPRSS2" ext_tax_ids="9606" ext_tax_names="Homo sapiens" ext_urls="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/gene/">TMPRSS2</sd-tag>) are all shown. Wilcoxon rank-sum test P value comparing the predicted positive targets to scrambled non-targeting siRNAs is given. <graphic href="https://api.sourcedata.io/file.php?panel_id=119843"/></sd-panel><sd-panel panel_id="119844">(C) Quantification of <sd-tag id="sdTag8" source="sdapi" category="assay" entity_type="None" role="None" text="cell number" ext_ids="BAO_0000572" ext_dbs="" in_caption="True" ext_names="cell number determination" ext_tax_ids="" ext_tax_names="" ext_urls="https://bioportal.bioontology.org/ontologies/BAO/?p=classes&amp;conceptid=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.bioassayontology.org%2Fbao%23">cell number</sd-tag> after each target knockdown, calculated as the mean fraction of <sd-tag id="sdTag9" source="sdapi" category="None" entity_type="molecule" role="reporter" text="DAPI" ext_ids="CHEBI:51231" ext_dbs="" in_caption="True" ext_names="DAPI" ext_tax_ids="" ext_tax_names="" ext_urls="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/chebi/searchId.do?chebiId=">DAPI</sd-tag>+ cells relative to the scrambled non-targeting siRNAs (i.e. the latter was normalized to 1). Colors of dots and P value are interpreted in the same way as in (B). <graphic href="https://api.sourcedata.io/file.php?panel_id=119844"/></sd-panel><sd-panel panel_id="119845">(D) Representative fluorescence images from the siRNA assay showing <sd-tag id="sdTag22" source="sdapi" category="None" entity_type="organism" role="assayed" text="SARS-CoV-2" ext_ids="2697049" ext_dbs="" in_caption="True" ext_names="Severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2" ext_tax_ids="" ext_tax_names="" ext_urls="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/taxonomy/">SARS-CoV-2</sd-tag> infection (green channel, top row), <sd-tag id="sdTag23" source="sdapi" category="assay" entity_type="None" role="None" text="cell number" ext_ids="BAO_0000572" ext_dbs="" in_caption="True" ext_names="cell number determination" ext_tax_ids="" ext_tax_names="" ext_urls="https://bioportal.bioontology.org/ontologies/BAO/?p=classes&amp;conceptid=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.bioassayontology.org%2Fbao%23">cell number</sd-tag> (blue channel, middle row) and merged (bottom row). Results for scrambled non-targeting siRNA as negative control (left column), knockdown of three predicted top metabolic targets (<sd-tag id="sdTag24" source="sdapi" category="None" entity_type="gene" role="intervention" text="PIKFYVE" ext_ids="200576" ext_dbs="" in_caption="True" ext_names="PIKFYVE" ext_tax_ids="9606" ext_tax_names="Homo sapiens" ext_urls="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/gene/">PIKFYVE</sd-tag>, <sd-tag id="sdTag25" source="sdapi" category="None" entity_type="gene" role="intervention" text="SLC16A10" ext_ids="117247" ext_dbs="" in_caption="True" ext_names="SLC16A10" ext_tax_ids="9606" ext_tax_names="Homo sapiens" ext_urls="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/gene/">SLC16A10</sd-tag>, and <sd-tag id="sdTag26" source="sdapi" category="None" entity_type="gene" role="intervention" text="PIP5K1C" ext_ids="23396" ext_dbs="" in_caption="True" ext_names="PIP5K1C" ext_tax_ids="9606" ext_tax_names="Homo sapiens" ext_urls="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/gene/">PIP5K1C</sd-tag>, middle columns), and knockdown of positive control (<sd-tag id="sdTag27" source="sdapi" category="None" entity_type="gene" role="component" text="ACE2" ext_ids="59272" ext_dbs="" in_caption="True" ext_names="ACE2" ext_tax_ids="9606" ext_tax_names="Homo sapiens" ext_urls="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/gene/">ACE2</sd-tag>, right column) are shown. Scale bar=10 μm. <graphic href="https://api.sourcedata.io/file.php?panel_id=119845"/></sd-panel></fig><fig id="43850"><title>.</title><label>Figure 5</label><graphic href="https://api.sourcedata.io/file.php?figure_id=43850"/><sd-panel panel_id="119846">(A) PCA plot of the <sd-tag id="sdTag28" source="sdapi" category="assay" entity_type="None" role="None" text="gene expression" ext_ids="BAO_0002785" ext_dbs="" in_caption="True" ext_names="gene expression assay" ext_tax_ids="" ext_tax_names="" ext_urls="https://bioportal.bioontology.org/ontologies/BAO/?p=classes&amp;conceptid=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.bioassayontology.org%2Fbao%23">gene expression</sd-tag> profiles for the <sd-tag id="sdTag29" source="sdapi" category="None" entity_type="cell" role="component" text="Vero E6" ext_ids="CVCL_0059" ext_dbs="" in_caption="True" ext_names="Vero" ext_tax_ids="60711" ext_tax_names="Chlorocebus sabaeus" ext_urls="https://identifiers.org/cellosaurus:">Vero E6</sd-tag> samples from all experimental groups: control (no virus or <sd-tag id="sdTag32" source="sdapi" category="None" entity_type="molecule" role="intervention" text="remdesivir" ext_ids="CHEBI:145994" ext_dbs="" in_caption="True" ext_names="remdesivir" ext_tax_ids="" ext_tax_names="" ext_urls="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/chebi/searchId.do?chebiId=">remdesivir</sd-tag> treatment), virus (<sd-tag id="sdTag30" source="sdapi" category="None" entity_type="organism" role="intervention" text="SARS-CoV-2" ext_ids="2697049" ext_dbs="" in_caption="True" ext_names="Severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2" ext_tax_ids="" ext_tax_names="" ext_urls="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/taxonomy/">SARS-CoV-2</sd-tag>-infected), virus+<sd-tag id="sdTag31" source="sdapi" category="None" entity_type="molecule" role="intervention" text="remdesivir" ext_ids="CHEBI:145994" ext_dbs="" in_caption="True" ext_names="remdesivir" ext_tax_ids="" ext_tax_names="" ext_urls="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/chebi/searchId.do?chebiId=">remdesivir</sd-tag> (<sd-tag id="sdTag33" source="sdapi" category="None" entity_type="organism" role="intervention" text="SARS-CoV-2" ext_ids="2697049" ext_dbs="" in_caption="True" ext_names="Severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2" ext_tax_ids="" ext_tax_names="" ext_urls="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/taxonomy/">SARS-CoV-2</sd-tag>-infected treated by <sd-tag id="sdTag34" source="sdapi" category="None" entity_type="molecule" role="intervention" text="remdesivir" ext_ids="CHEBI:145994" ext_dbs="" in_caption="True" ext_names="remdesivir" ext_tax_ids="" ext_tax_names="" ext_urls="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/chebi/searchId.do?chebiId=">remdesivir</sd-tag>), <sd-tag id="sdTag35" source="sdapi" category="None" entity_type="molecule" role="intervention" text="remdesivir" ext_ids="CHEBI:145994" ext_dbs="" in_caption="True" ext_names="remdesivir" ext_tax_ids="" ext_tax_names="" ext_urls="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/chebi/searchId.do?chebiId=">remdesivir</sd-tag> (<sd-tag id="sdTag36" source="sdapi" category="None" entity_type="molecule" role="intervention" text="remdesivir" ext_ids="CHEBI:145994" ext_dbs="" in_caption="True" ext_names="remdesivir" ext_tax_ids="" ext_tax_names="" ext_urls="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/chebi/searchId.do?chebiId=">remdesivir</sd-tag> treatment alone without virus). There are 3 replicates in each group. <graphic href="https://api.sourcedata.io/file.php?panel_id=119846"/></sd-panel><sd-panel panel_id="119847">(B) A visualization of selected differentially expressed pathways comparing the virus+<sd-pretag id="sdPretag1804701856sd" parent-tag-id="31">remdesivir</sd-pretag> group to the control group using gene set enrichment analysis (<sd-pretag id="sdPretag1663918120sd" category="assay">GSEA</sd-pretag>). Y-axis represents normalized enrichment score (<sd-pretag id="sdPretag44351443sd" type="geneprod" role="component">NES</sd-pretag>), positive value means higher expression in the virus+<sd-pretag id="sdPretag1456232229sd" parent-tag-id="31">remdesivir</sd-pretag> group compared to control, vice versa. The dashed line corresponds to <sd-pretag id="sdPretag316601274sd" type="geneprod" role="component">NES</sd-pretag>=0 (i.e. separating positive and negative enrichment). Pathways on the X-axis are ordered by their <sd-pretag id="sdPretag312323195sd" type="geneprod" role="component">NES</sd-pretag> values, all pathways displayed have adjusted P&lt;0.05; pathways with names in red are those that are not significantly different (adjusted P&gt;0.2) when comparing the virus group to the control group using <sd-pretag id="sdPretag1112243898sd" category="assay">GSEA</sd-pretag>, i.e. changes in these pathways may arise from <sd-pretag id="sdPretag1044515273sd" parent-tag-id="31">remdesivir</sd-pretag>-specific effects. The dot color corresponds to the negative log10 adjusted <sd-pretag id="sdPretag1043617536sd" category="assay">GSEA</sd-pretag> P value, and dot size corresponds to the number of enriched genes (i.e. "leading edge" genes in <sd-pretag id="sdPretag249109655sd" category="assay">GSEA</sd-pretag>). <graphic href="https://api.sourcedata.io/file.php?panel_id=119847"/></sd-panel><sd-panel panel_id="119848">(C) PCA plot of the average <sd-tag id="sdTag50" source="sdapi" category="assay" entity_type="None" role="None" text="metabolic flux profile" ext_ids="OBI_0000366" ext_dbs="" in_caption="True" ext_names="metabolite profiling" ext_tax_ids="" ext_tax_names="" ext_urls="http://www.ontobee.org/ontology/OBI?iri=http://purl.obolibrary.org/obo/">metabolic flux profile</sd-tag> computed using the iMAT algorithm (Shlomi et al. 2008; Methods) representative of each of the experimental groups, the labels are the same as (A). <graphic href="https://api.sourcedata.io/file.php?panel_id=119848"/></sd-panel><sd-panel panel_id="119849">(D) A visualization of metabolic pathway enrichment results of the differential metabolic fluxes in the virus+<sd-pretag id="sdPretag760358430sd" parent-tag-id="31">remdesivir</sd-pretag> group vs the control group, using Fisher's exact tests (Methods). Y-axis represents the odds ratio of enrichment, the horizontal dashed line corresponds to odds ratio of 1. The dot color corresponds to the negative log10 adjusted one-sided P value from Fisher's exact tests, and dot size corresponds to the number of enriched target reactions. The datasets are ordered by P values, all pathways displayed have FDR&lt;0.1. <graphic href="https://api.sourcedata.io/file.php?panel_id=119849"/></sd-panel><sd-panel panel_id="119850">(E) The robust metabolic transformation algorithm (rMTA, Valcárcel et al. 2019) was used to predict metabolic reactions whose knock-out can further transform the metabolic state of the <sd-pretag id="sdPretag762292369sd" parent-tag-id="31">remdesivir</sd-pretag>-treated SARS-CoV-2-infected cells back to the normal control state, using the Vero E6 cell samples (Methods). The significant metabolic pathways (FDR&lt;0.1) enriched by the top 10% MTA-predicted targets are shown. Axes and the meanings of dot color and size are similar to (D). <graphic href="https://api.sourcedata.io/file.php?panel_id=119850"/></sd-panel></fig></article>